[Music]
so today I'm going to talk about how AI
coding is evolving as a
product and it's going to be fun right
uh we've been all excited about this for
more than a year and a half two years
it's been fun my name is Patrick D I
have a very particular style I show a
lot of quick slides but no worries you
can watch the demo the video and the
slides later so it's all fun uh to get
there all right so let's kick it in we
have topt go right everybody knows the
co-pilot the thing that we do we write
some comments and low and behold AI
completed this this is what most people
know from there this is the quick intro
that kind of things like chat GPT came
and all of a sudden we have chat copy
paste instead of just tap tap go right
so we ask it a question it generates
some of the code and then we'll look at
it we read it and then if you're really
happy with this we do copy and paste in
our IDE that's what most people know but
that is not at all what we're going to
talk about we're going to go go way
further than that so first part what's
all new what what are the crazy new
features that we are seeing popping up
in all the
tools first thing is instead of of copy
and pasting we can just apply it like
just get rid of that copy and paste
method why are we still doing there we
just say apply this to our file all good
instant apply now if you've been doing
the tab completion why does it only show
one line now we finally have multi-line
edits and it's showing a complete block
editing instead of having to tap tap tap
continuously for the next line much of
an
improvement but it can even go further
we have the taptap completion but the
tapt is not always kind of the next line
it's trying to predict what is actually
the next thing so if I'm editing a
function below and all of a sudden I'm
typing tap it predicts that I'm going to
go on first line and it actually jumps
for me
a lot of improvements these are typical
things that are now happening IDE but we
didn't have it just from the
beginning then when all the models
Beyond open AI GPT came out we are
finally able to bring our own model in
most of the IDE tools it's funny that
the one advantage that we were thinking
what oh the model is going to be the
unique thing all of the editors are
opening up to one of the SAS providers
and even running l LS locally there so
big Improvement for privacy for stuff
and it seems like they're almost giving
up to the things they do with the model
and giving it directly also saves costs
I'll be honest now with the reasoning
model like in 01 in open AI we saw that
we're switching between two different
kind of models one is for the editing
and the other one is generating the
tasks in this example ader one of the
tools is leveraging this reasoning as
looking at the code as an architect
again this is a new thing you'll see
come up more and more in the editing
tools of the coding
IDs instead of just looking at the one
file it's going to index my code base
well gup has been doing indexing for all
that GitHub repos but now it starts also
indexing my stuff locally which give it
a better understanding of giving
actually m style or the things that I
want to do with my code and then we've
talked about this um generating tests
but what about generating tests looking
at the test coverage another great
feature that helps us kind of generate
more more particular more on brand what
we need to code all new features very
exciting and they're existing there
today even though it says
experimental now it really get excited
on coding when cursor opened up the
floor with multifile edits I give it a
prompt and all of a sudden it's not just
changing it in line it's changing in one
file another file and more and more that
has been a lifesaver all of a sudden you
get like more impact on all the files
feature that exists
today and then I found myself Less typ
in code I started to do continuous
prompting and if I didn't like the
result that he gave me after reviewing
the code I just gave a follow-up prompt
and that kind of led me to almost
continuous prompting and hardly touching
the code but more reviewing the code
it's amazing the speed has gone through
the roof for me kind of developing new
applications
now what can we do to even make it
better and there's been a constant thing
as these llms try to eat more data more
context so what have we done to get more
context in or IDE now this is the second
part context first is by having an at
okay I'm not just typing the question
I'm specifying which file I want to do
but there's way more context that I can
do I can add a terminal I can add my
documentation folder a URL do and kind
of even my tickets those are features
that exist today that will enhance your
workflow just beyond the simp simple
code Generation by having context
providers and I can even reference my
whole uh kind of workspace at workspace
that understands the whole of my code
with everything in it if it has my front
end code my backend code it will change
both at the same time things that work
today now there's been some helpers to
get the context in this is one fun thing
which is kind of play on GitHub UB which
takes URL and actually allows you to add
that into a code so it creates like one
big file of that context of an external
rapo useful if you want to bring on like
a library a framework or how to do
things or maybe code from somebody
else now documentation is an easy one
that is web crawling uh you can see here
the the dump of all the docs that are
available in cursor uh all the
documentations of the Frameworks that
you can use so if it has a documentation
of the framework and your code and it
knows which version you're running on
you can get amazing better results than
just having the code generation because
these are up toate these can be updated
and added at your own time even if you
have local documentation in your Wiki or
wherever you can add the documentation
to your
sources now again another tool to take
whatever URL even a YouTube video an npm
package or it doesn't matter to add
context it so you see there's a real
Drive of getting more context in your
IDE to give it better results
now we've seen a few technical tools
that do that for you but you even start
seeing vendors applying this and
optimizing their documentation to be
used as a context that's a nice side
effect so we don't have to kind of have
it in between but much like SEO or
mobile optimize we're going to have ai
optimized documentation uh to be
used now documentation is one thing but
maybe you have a coding style and you're
some kind of community whether that's
next GS or python or JavaScript or Java
they all kind of have their conventions
so you have the code you have the
documentation and now you can bring in
kind of the requirements in a way that
you know how we do things how that world
works even even if it's a new language
that has not been indexed or is not
available on any of the chat gpts I've C
it in Objective C right there's not a
lot of models that have been trained but
this was a lifesaver to do that now
let's go further what can we do got
documentation code all that stuff people
been craving about can you please find
you how we do things around here and get
up co-pilot was one of the first to say
well we can f tune but it's it's a
double-edged sort at the one hand you
those kind of Corporations don't want
their stuff to be trained on their uh
kind of publicly and on the other hand
they're craving to have their own style
defined so this was a bit slippery scope
and I don't think that uh it has gone
like completely J yet but how do we kind
of get around this now much like the
documentation why not have a set of
rules how we do things uh and I
mentioned before with the identities of
a certain coder but you can specify your
own rules this is how I want my mobile
development this is my directory
structure this is how I set up my
databases so you have a personal style
even beyond the Frameworks or your
company style that you can bring in that
rules and now again you can add those
rules into the context while asking
something to the
llm even bringing in a component because
not just the documentation but you say I
want this kind of UI component to be
used in my front end and then in
translate that or this framework I want
to be used so that's another way of
bringing in context Beyond kind of
simple code uh and uh text
generation so we looked at all of the
new stuff we shown that there was an
amazing things that you Cann now bring
into the context now where does it all
lead to like we been generating it's
getting better and better and we all
know like a lot of projects actually
start with designs and this is a tool
that kind of generates designs tap all
the complete designs and most of the
time you actually have a mockup of a
screen that you need to implement now
you now have the way to upload a design
do I Implement how do I implement the
similar UI to this screenshot this
design those kind of functions now exist
thanks to the multimodel solutions and
give you a kind of good head start and
you can even use this when it goes wrong
like I don't want it to look like this
but I want it to look like that again
powerful features that have been added
to
it now you started seeing more and more
of the developers keeping a sessions of
what they've been doing on their own
style but also on the specifics of the
project and the decisions they've taken
and kind of the steps it's almost like
your change log that functionality keeps
memory and it's really interesting that
people started to use this as context
because it remembered all the previous
specifications that were
required okay so I have
specifications and then we have another
way like given the specifications buildt
me a plan so this is really helpful to
kind of see the first steps the next
steps so internally
when you ask it a prompt there is a
translation to a set of steps first do
this then do that and that's kind of
part of that reasoning that has built a
plan u in the keynote it was mentioned
that okay we're going to go for some
things in the chat some things in the
editor and we're going to go to more
specifications and we're going to drive
a plan and eventually we're going to get
to code that's really cool and I think
you know kind of taking these specs and
making them part of the the coding uh as
similar to adrs or decisions or
specifications is a great way to keep
them kind of together and to remember
kind of the decisions so we're going
from specs to
implementation and then if you really
want to go further we're just looking at
all the product requirements the feature
set and we're doing a mixture between
this is how we want things um and this
is what we want things and that kind of
mixture is a really powerful combo to
bring things together and being
generated now we have the
specifications and it's generating a
massive amount of coding and I feel that
our job is changing from coding to
coding being generated and the thing we
do more and more is actually reviewing
the code so what can we do to make that
life easier because the bottleneck has
now shifted to
that there's been interesting things
like a I'm changing code we're very used
to the diff view we've seen that there's
a chat view trying to explain the things
that we do but we can now use actually
AI to reduce the cognitive load by
saying these thing have changed this
matters so for example existing code
takes away what of the boilerplate
remove the I at the end of the next line
that is the description of a condensed
view um that it has done so that helps
us faster reviewing of the code that's
been generated now another kind of way
of improving that review is to break it
down in a lot of different steps like
this file has changed because of that
reason that file has changed because if
we're just seeing one big div it's going
to overload our brains and it's really
nice that we start seeing partial
acceptance of this file is good this one
I want to PR uh change this one I want
to improve so that's another kind of
improvement in cognitive
load
now this can increase because generation
is cheap so maybe we're not seeing one
version but we're seeing multiple
versions in this case the front end has
three flavors and we'll have to pick one
we can give feedback that improves
actually the generation but it is
interesting to see that the cost is
going down so we can make make better
choices there as well now what we all
love is instant feedback right and I ask
here to create a video application and
lo and behold we've all been rickrolled
because that's what it does but the
important part is that what we building
we want to see how it works that
feedback is so crucial and that is uh
one of the things that we're seeing more
and more in the tools is that the
representation and the impact is shown
to us
now this slide is a bit fuzzy but it
shows that we have specifications on the
left and coding on the right and we want
to be able to switch between both uh
easily and if the coding change we want
our documentation updated or
specification and if a specification
change we actually want to code to
update so that kind of binary view uh is
an important aspect that we're seeing
more and more in idees uh coming up now
it doesn't have to be Tex
in this case I'm generating
infrastructure as code and it's showing
me diagrams or the impact of things in a
different way so I know there's code but
I can handle the cognitive load of the
change in another way of looking at
things I can have visualizations of the
whole code base to understand what the
impact what the change is again just an
example of a different way of
visualizing the code and having me sort
out different kind of problems
now it's not only about having different
views I can have different modalities
maybe I want to do voice coding because
let's face it we're typing more and more
as a prompt so why can't I just talk to
the machine and it comes back I'm hardly
typing code which was hard for us to
kind of like say you know open colon and
all that stuff now I just need to ask
and give it a natural language follow
up we're seeing new ways of exploring
code think of it as canvas but canvas
with code and requirements and Designs
mixed together this is a great way of
having multiple views on the code uh and
your
specifications now even you know
notebooks are something that is very
popular with the the data science folks
uh we're seeing this as executable
documentation or code uh of your Cloud
environments so a different kind of new
hybrid development environment is kind
of emerging from those things as well
for different reviews or different
understandings uh of what has been
changed So eventually we want actually
the editor to adapt to the mental model
of the user so not just the text editor
but maybe a domain specific or problem
specific thing that we want to
solve okay we got the editor we're able
to review that kind of got better now
what do we do about the trust right
because that's the big thing how much do
we trust that
stuff um Devin was one of the first ones
who actually kind of uh showed us that
there's a feedback loop from hey the
chat is going here's the requirements
and then kind of the the browser and the
editor and a shell they all work in a
continuous feedback Lo
system so here you see uh kind of the
run it's looking at what it's in the
browser it's copy and pasting much as I
said then it's looking at kind of the
the terminal it's getting the error and
changing the code this is a really
powerful Improvement Loop that we've
seen um that kind of takes a lot of the
boiler plate that we've been doing
manually and that's often when you do
automations is that more and more as you
get more confident is that automation
take
place we can get termal feedback right
there's an error in the termal and we
can add it to the chat or we can add it
to fix this code uh in our conversations
with AI so that's one way we can have
browser error feedback you know there's
actually also an AI in kind of a chrome
now that explains things uh and can fit
this back into your code editors as
well now the big thing is we have
linting and we have errors but it is
indeed about execution and we're still
challenged on how do we do this well
we're run it in a sandbox is it going to
be a preview Branch how do we get the
feedback um like this is an example
almost from having a shadow environment
where the AI is working on and kind of
exploring different ways uh to check
things whether they're still okay and
they're still
executable we can check for breaking
changes from apis um like I changed
something did the documentation uh what
was changed explained that to me as well
so more invisibility on kind of when
things change uh and would break things
uh but I can also look things as
remember you're refactoring a a big kind
of Legacy code did we reduce the code
quality okay I have code coverage I have
specific things but also code
familiarity like do I still understand
the code uh when I read this there so a
tool like code scene actually helps to
keep track of those metrics as well and
they will feed into the feedback loop of
improving stuff as well
I can do automated trat modeling on my
code feed that in as feedback there's no
thing that like all the tools we've been
building we could feed this back into
that AI Loop to improve um and that
becomes really funny when we we actually
kind of trust the system to commit I had
like I was very uh kind of uh torn
between should I allow autoc commit or
uh do I I still verify certain things uh
and it's about like the threshold of how
certain thei is of a certain commit I
can still revoke this of course but
there's a question like how do we know
it's good enough how do we actually do
this ourselves uh to know that it's good
enough we can go back with Version
Control so similar in that conversation
we can roll back to a checkpoint uh
before and check in check out the
changes uh obviously there's things like
data that need to be adapted but this is
very similar how we deal with kind of
failures in our environments
already and now we have one agent kind
of coding the stuff but what if I have
multiple things right so it's just going
to be so complex for these things to
create uh to for us to manage what they
all create uh so we need to have a
certain level of autonomy or we will hit
a bottleneck of us reviewing these
things all the time
now it even gets more interesting is
that instead of just seeing fixing the
errors we also want these tools to look
for knowledge uh so if I ask a question
I feed a documentation I feed certain
things it will ask now is this something
that is important should we save this as
a fact right this is another way of
becoming more autonomous is if it knows
what to do but you know it asks us for
knowledge and then the next time he
actually
knows now we can go even further why are
we still replying to PRS it has all the
context it has our code it has the way
we want to do things so let's have it
just have answers of colleagues and get
feedback back into the code there's
nothing stopping us there and feeding it
back yes we still say do we allow it yes
or no but that's kind of the trend that
we're going for in those coding tools
and to kick it off at the end this is a
tool that actually improves their code
uh through AB testing with end user
feedback are we going to go that far
that we're taking into the end user
feedback and have it changeed your code
or our configs from production as well
very interesting times uh to reflect on
now I personally had it multiple times
that the AI started changing my
specification files so I also want a
mechanism to say AI you cannot touch
these things log the file is one example
I found but maybe want to say things
that it cannot change or touches
everything uh so it becomes more like an
access control what the agent can do
what the human can do what the override
are as well now I think what I've shown
you it is there out there it is not
somewhere kind of in a lab and it's
really powerful uh and I hope I've shown
you kind of the different ways that you
know the products of AI development have
evolved to new things and we're in an
era that we have to stop building the
things but we build the things that
build the things right that is the new
level of development that is happening
that is the abstraction level that we're
going
for here's a bunch of people that I
really enjoy watching on LinkedIn or
YouTube or x uh and they gave me a feed
of either new tool to or Reflections or
new things they do really good you can
obviously also subscribe to my YouTube
channel it has all my talks uh that you
can use uh and listen to if you want to
and let's open the floor for questions
um if you want slides connect to me on
LinkedIn um and I would say this is the
end awesome yeah absolutely connect to
connect to Patrick uh if you're not
connected with Patrick on LinkedIn or
anything like that um you know you're
you're being ridiculous so connect
connect connect and and and chat um
Patrick a very very thoughtful uh
session again I'd love to ask actually
because you maybe I should have asked uh
Lisa this as well um I wanted to ask you
know when you show a lot of tools like
this what what is your ideal kind of
like uh uh set up an environment looks
look like when you when you're when
you're building not just playing but
building
um my go-to ID right now is cursor
um but I also am very it seems like it's
quite easy to swap things in TT and out
so yes I've been using vzer as well I've
been using GPT engineer for other stuff
um I just evaluated win Sur uh wind surf
I think um which is giving a little bit
results the nice thing is they're all
kind of copying and mimicking the IDE in
this case uh from vs code so all the
plugins apply so you just open it in
whatever tool is the next uh best in the
race uh and I don't care too much like
as long and they have like the similar
uh Keys uh and solve problems for me
there is still a little bit of glue code
to be done for certain things like
browser feedback and you know but that
will just be a matter of time of being
implemented uh like what we can do man
ually we can automate um on that
perspective so that's kind of pretty
much my stack yeah absolutely I got a
question in here from aie uh AI asks
first of all says thanks for great
summary of the features um how do you
see the products ux development to be
Amplified by AI so I presume that means
building uh building or how do you how
do you consider the the ux of the
product you are building perhaps um
being Amplified by a yeah so the um I I
touched on it a little bit brief briefly
with the kind of the the the front end
design um where you have the
specifications of the user flows and the
personas um this is right now not
something that's very well connected in
the tools but I I would believe that
this is much like the requirements of
the technical requirements which you see
now most in the tools will become part
of the business requirements um and
these were the best examples I could
find yet but um there's a certain
disconnect between the two worlds and
people building tools right now but it
it's just going to get together closer I
think feedback from let's say analytics
I've shown the example of the AB testing
uh actual users uh what is important
what is not important imagine you feed
that back as a requirement or as a fact
um that that kind of can open up a new
kind of cycle of feedback uh while
developing uh new features as well yeah
yeah and and do you feel like with these
AI um powered tools or assistance as it
were do you feel like the the role of a
dev has actually changed that much or
has it just been enhanced or or um in
increased productivity but workflow
hasn't really changed that much is that
is that fair or do you think that's not
giving Justice to to what the AI has
changed I think the way I could has
changed that I I I mentioned that I'm
mostly using prompts uh I do the
occasional coding tweak but because I
still know coding I understand what I
actually want in the coding uh I had it
a few times when I didn't set up the
right doc directory structure that it
kind of uh I couldn't understand it
after five iterations how it went so
there's there kind of moving towards
more architecture or design decisions on
the technical part um and I think we're
getting closer to
spending more time on the business
requirements and say oh this is
incomplete we need this oh yeah it
generated like that but I didn't like it
like that so that kind of iteration is
is happening more on the failure yes
you're still the developer and you have
to sort it out uh the tools kind of help
more and more uh fixing the tools um but
I I think it's it's still important that
you understand what good looks like so
maybe we'll have to train more and read
more and kind of read more
documentation on kind of coding
guidelines there as well so that that is
how I think it's uh it's changing uh
it's ironically a little bit more Ops
than it is Dev like we're babysitting
part of the agents doing stuff and kind
of nudging it in the right direction and
dealing with failure uh so for me that's
a small irony in the world awesome
couple more questions let's see if we
can get through them in a couple of
minutes um uh farath asks looking
forward what are a few hypothetical
product features that you think would be
great um I think
feeding things in from production more
um there's still a heavy disconnect
between the two
tools uh I had a discussion about oh
let's feed it in logs and I've shown you
in the loop oh yeah it looks at it's on
logs and being executed but what about
looking at the production logs and the
things that actually fail so kind of
that would open up a new hurdle uh kind
of like not a hurdle but a new door for
all of a sudden you see things that it
should do um this could also help in
judging the impact of changes oh it's
only used by two
people uh while it could be two people
that pay a lot of money so that's
another Factor but kind of those kind of
feedback loops on service levels uh is
there as well that's interesting
actually because that that also makes me
think a a little bit about the next
session which is happening in around the
performance of code and being able to
almost it's that feedback loop right of
being able to say well let's understand
the real performance in production and
can we actually pull that back into into
design and and development decisions um
D Dan harder on as well hey Dan good to
good to good to see you joining us um
when using cursor or Kai pilot um and
using prompt driven development I love
that uh I find that I frequently find
the implementation breaks in a way that
AI can't figure out how do you deal with
these sorts of dead ends yeah
so imagine you've given it like 50
prompts and you would paste them all in
one big file and say hey use this
specification likely this will not work
um I have learned that you really have
to do small steps almost like a
developer incremental steps have a test
have a verification in there so the
smaller the step of the less I found
that it breaks actually the
implementations
I do see Rabbit Hole sometimes I say
it's not good it tells me it should be
like this um I've basically done a reset
of the conversation then and then I kind
of like say well forget everything else
just start a fresh and I give it a new
hint and sometimes that better because
it kind of like takes another almost
it's not taking another seed but it's
kind of like initializing a fresh
conversation uh almost like a fresh view
on the problem there as well so that's
what I've done there yeah that's similar
to actually guy Felipe I know a friend
uh of of the the company as well um
Filipe was talking about how once he's
had a conversation and turns into a dead
end what he does is he asks that that
you know the the llm there to almost
summarize what it had learned and then
using that to start almost a new
conversation but it's extremely hard to
remove that context or try and adapt the
existing context it's it's actually
easier to start start a fresh very
interesting and the last question um
Patrick according to you uh bries from
from bries According to you which tool
do you think think is best for figma to
code for next
JS um I'm not the front end uh
specialist but um I think you know figma
probably has some kind of integration to
it but uh I'm mostly using the the vzer
to kind of the versal thing to kind of
get things but I don't know if it has a
direct integration with figma as well
yeah okay it exists why don't we thr
that out into the into the into the chat
again um if anyone's using uh front end
what is uh what is the best for figma to
code for nextjs um that that people
think in the in the chat give your
answers um for now though Patrick
another very inspiring uh session thank
you so so much for being a part of the
inative Devcon and thank you for your
session today my pleasure